Finding Aid for Vittorio Re papers, 1921-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vittorio Re papers 1921-2005
Re, Vittorio.
2010054 Aa 2
Correspondence, writings, research, and collected materials of Vittorio Re, Chief Chancellor of the Italian Consulate in Detroit, and noted author and lecturer on the history and experiences of the Italian-American community in Detroit and the state of Michigan.
4.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection received from Vittorio Re (donor no. 10307 )in January, 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Vittorio Re entered the Italian Consular Service on April 15, 1933 as administrative assistant at the Italian Consulate General of Sydney, Australia. After serving in the Italian Consulate General in Dubrovnic, Yugoslavia and the Italian Foreign Ministry Rome, he was appointed Chief Chancellor of the Italian Consulate in Detroit, Michigan, where his main interests were in commercial, cultural, and community relations.
Re holds an Italian Diploma in Education from the Teachers Training Institute in Rome and a B.A. in History from Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan. He was a Knight in the Order of Merit of the Italian Republic.
After his retirement in 1977 he dedicated his time to researching the life of Italians in Michigan. His first effort was a history of the First Italian Presbyterian Church, followed by research on numerous topics related to the Italians of Michigan and the city of Detroit.
The Vittorio Re collection includes personal and professional papers, as well as collected materials, related to Mr. Re's position as Chief Chancellor of the Italian Consulate in Detroit, and his research and writings on the Italian community in Michigan and Detroit. The collection is especially rich with material about life and activities of Italian communities in Michigan, prominent Americans of Italian decent, as well as discrimination and stereotypes faced by the members of Italian American community. The papers are arranged in the following series: Correspondence and Notes; Papers, Speeches, and Research; and Collected Materials.
Subjects:
Re, Vittorio.; DeGaetano, Armand L.; Gelli, Giovanni Battista, 1498-1563.; Detroit (Mich.); American Italian Historical Association.; Italian American Cultural Society (Mich.); Columbus Day.; Italian Americans--Michigan.; Italian Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Organized crime--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Audiotapes.; Photographs.
- Correspondence and notes
  The Correspondence and Notes series includes both personal and professional letters as well some of Re's notes, covering the period from 1952 to 2002.
  - Personal correspondence 1952-2002 (Box 1)
  - Professional papers and correspondence 1922-2005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Isotta Horraver Cesari 1990-1997 (Box 1)
  - Notes (Box 1)
- Papers, speeches, research
  Papers, Speeches, and Research contains assignments and papers written by Re while a student at Wayne State University; papers and speeches written during his professional career as Chief Chancellor of the Italian Consulate; and papers about the history of Italians in the city of Detroit and the state of Michigan written after his retirement in 1977. Handwritten notes, publications, and printed materials collected by Re to support his writings are included.
  - Papers
    - Papers, blue books written while a student at Wayne State University, Detroit 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - "Italians in Michigan," chapter for The Italian Experience in America, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    - "Andrea Aguiar: Black Hero of the Italian Risorgimento," correspondence, notes, original manuscript with photographs 1978-2004 (Box 1)
    - "The Language of the Old Italo-American," undated (Box 1)
    - "Ciccio e Peppino," 1997-2004 (Box 1)
    - "Francois Fontenay Dit L'Espagnole," undated (Box 1)
    - La Storia Degli Esuli Messinesi Del 1678-79 undated (Box 1)
    - "The Italians," Italian Americans of Detroit and Michigan 1982 (Box 1)
    - "L'Affondamento della Central America 1992-1998 (Box 1)
    - "Italians in Michigan," "Michigan's Italian Community: a historical perspective," "History of the First Italian Presbyterian Church in Detroit," 1981-1996 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous papers and notes (one folder)
      - "Before and After Columbus," June 2, 1986 (Box 1)
      - "Elections in 1992" undated (Box 1)
      - "Einstein," undated (Box 1)
      - "At the Barber Shop," January 23, 1993 (Box 1)
      - "Emotions of Love," Valentine's Day 1989 (Box 1)
      - "Thomas Morton," March 10, 1987 (Box 1)
      - "A souvenir of the 25th years anniversary of their marriage," September 11, 1992 (Box 1)
      - Letters to the editor regarding discrimination against Italians (Box 1)
      - "L'imprapocchio," undated (Box 1)
      - "NCS1 and US Foreign Policy towards Italy," undated (Box 1)
      - "Mamma Mia," undated (Box 1)
      - Notes and incomplete (most in Italian) (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - "Before and After Columbus," undated (Box 1)
    - Guest speech, Columbus Day Banquet and Celebration, Lansing Michigan October 11, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Columbus Day speech in Columet, Michigan 1976 (Box 1)
    - "Terrorism: historical aspects of its origin and its influence on Italy," Prismatic Club 1979 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan's Italian Community," 24th Annual Conference in Local History April 16-17, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Nostalgia of the immigrants, including original and translated poems of Italo-Americans April 14, 1986 (Box 1)
    - "One Hundred Years Before and After Columbus," Prismatic Club June 2, 1986 (Box 1)
    - A view of what Italy was 100 years before the discovery of America, Troy Study Group October 2, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Essays on the discovery of America, Prismatic Club 1992 (Box 1)
    - Speech, Human Rights Department, Detroit Mich. 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Giacomo DeMartino (Box 1)
    - Untitled undated (Box 1)
  - Research
    - Alfonso Tonti (Box 1)
    - Amerigo Vespucci (Box 1)
    - Anthony Maiullo (Box 1)
    - Census information, Italians in Michigan and the US 1820-1970 (Box 1)
    - "I Have a Dream" by Martin Luther King, translated into Italian by Re May, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Italians in Michigan
      - Genovese in Detroit (Box 1)
      - Italians in Detroit, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Italians in Michigan and Detroit before 1850 (documents, notes, correspondence, lists) (Box 1)
      - Italians in Michigan Labor Unions (Box 1)
      - Italians in the Upper Peninsula (Box 1)
      - Italian women of Detroit (Box 2)
      - Lombards in Detroit (Box 2)
      - Sicilians in Detroit (Box 2)
      - Southern Italians in Detroit (Box 2)
    - Leonard W. Moss (Box 2)
    - Mafia in Michigan and Detroit
      - McClellan investigation (clippings) (Box 2)
      - Newspaper clippings 1950s-1990s, 8 folders (Box 2)
      - Research files (Box 2)
    - Monsignor Ciarrocchi (Box 3)
    - Pasquale Palmieri (Box 3)
    - Pietro Cardiello -- Vice Consul for Italy in Detroit (Box 3)
    - Publications
      - Italian newspapers and journals in the U.S. (Box 3)
      - Notizie della Italia (Box 3)
    - Vincenzo Giuliano (Box 3)
    - World War I
      - Italians who volunteered and died in WWI (lists) (Box 3)
      - Research files (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 3)
- Collected materials
  Collected Materials contains brochures, publicity materials, notes, and correspondence associated with Italian organizations, as well as events in the Italian community of Michigan. The collection includes information about the bylaws, membership, elections, and events of the Michigan chapter of the American Italian Historical Association. Materials on the 500th anniversary celebration of Columbus Day are included, 700th anniversary of Dante, and 100th anniversary of Garibaldi's death. There are numerous newspaper clippings in English and Italian associated with events, people, and issues relevant to the Italian community in Detroit and Michigan. Also, papers of Armand L. DeGaetano, given to Mr. Re by DeGaetano. Armand DeGaetano was Professor of Italian at Wayne State University in Detroit, active member and leader of a number of Italian American organizations concerned with teaching of the Italian language and culture in the United States and in Michigan in particular. Papers include correspondence, personal and professional files, and heavily annotated and edited draft manuscript of a 1954 biography of Giovanni Battista Gelli by Lucy Moore (?), sent to DeGaetano by the author.
  - DeGaetano, Armand L. papers
    - Correspondence 1956-1969 (Box 3)
    - Giovanni Battista Gelli biography 1954, 13 folders (Box 3)
    - Italian American organizations 1958-1969 (with gaps) (Box 3)
    - Lectures 1955 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - Personal (Box 3)
  - Italian Organizations in Michigan
    - American Italian Historical Association, Michigan Chapter
      - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 3)
      - Articles of Incorporation (Box 3)
      - Elections 1982-1988 (Box 3)
      - Membership (Box 3)
      - Dues and Finances (Box 3)
      - Annual Reports (Box 3)
      - Newsletters (Box 3)
      - Conferences
        - November 12-15, 1987 (Box 3)
        - November 12-14, 1992 (Box 3)
        - 1985-1997 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Italian American Cultural Society, Michigan Chapter
      - Library Archives (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Conferences (Box 4)
        - November 6-8, 1981 (Box 4)
        - Joint conference with American Italian Historical Association 1987 (Box 4)
    - Churches in Detroit
      - San Francisco Church (Box 4)
      - Holy Family Church (Box 4)
      - Italian Methodist Church (Box 4)
      - First Italian Baptist Church (Box 4)
    - Other organizations in Michigan
      - Italian Societies, miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Italian Benevolent Society (Box 4)
      - Dante Alighieri Society (Box 4)
      - Italy America Society (Box 4)
      - Italian American Chamber of Commerce (Box 3)
      - Italian Consulate: Comites (Committee for Italian Citizens Abroad) of Detroit, Michigan, 2 folders (Box 4)
        (assists Italian community with programs and information from the Italian Consulate)
      - Italian Library of the Cultural Center (Box 4)
      - Italian Study Group of Troy (Box 4)
      - Sons of Italy (Box 4)
  - Italian organizations, outside Michigan
    - Crusaders Academy of Science undated (Box 4)
    - Crusaders Order of the World 1939-1941 (Box 4)
  - Italians outside Michigan 1935-1938 (Box 4)
  - Events
    - Visit of General Diaz 1921 (Box 4)
    - Columbus Day
      - Celebrations 1937-1986 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - Quincentenary Celebration 1992
        - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Publications (Box 4)
      - Souvenir booklets, 1 folders
        - 1892 Philadelphia (Box 4)
        - 1966 (Box 4)
        - 1974 (Box 4)
        - 1994 (Box 4)
    - Centennial Celebration of Italian Unification, Detroit, Mich. May 21, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Conference on the Contributions of Italians to the United States April, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Dante's Septuacentennial 1965 (Box 5)
    - Giuseppe Garibaldi death centennial 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Ethnic Conference, Ann Arbor, Mich. June, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - English language, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Italian language, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Magnetic audio tape, "San Marino Club" (Box 5)